翻译    Saniac, Ling, ZSC   校对    ksyx
时间轴    博美子
I realized recently that I didn't really understand how a prism works,
最近我发现自己并没有真正理解棱镜是怎么工作的
and I suspect most people out there don't either.
我猜大多数人也不大理解
Arguably this is one of the most widely recognized physics experiments ever.
从某种意义上来说 这是最广为人知的物理实验之一
After all, how many others have earned a place as an iconic album cover?
毕竟 有多少实验能成为专辑封面呢？
Sure, some of Pink Floyd's design choices run completely contrary to the actual physics.
当然 Pink Floyd 的一些设计是违背物理学规律的
Like why did they make the light inside the prism white?
比如说 为什么要把棱镜里的光设计成白色呢？
And bafflingly, why would you draw all the colors as a discrete set,
更令人费解的是 为什么要像小孩子画彩虹一样
like a child making a rainbow,
把所有颜色画成离散的呢
despite the fact that one of the key points in Newton's original experiment involving prisms
要知道牛顿棱镜实验的一个关键点
was that sunlight contains a continuous spectrum of colors?
就是太阳光包含了连续的光谱
Still, setting that aside, it's cool that it's in pop culture at all,
但不管怎样 这个实验能在流行文化中出现就已经很酷了
and any self-respecting physics enthusiast should know how it works,
而且每个合格的物理爱好者  都应该知道它是怎么工作的
but the thing I realized is that my understanding hit a wall pretty quickly if pressed.
但我发现  如果深究起来  我的理解很快就会遇到瓶颈
You see, the standard explanation,
你想  常规的解释
what you might hear in a high school physics class for example, goes something like this.
例如高中物理课上教的  可能会说
When light enters a medium, like glass, it slows down,
光在进入诸如玻璃的介质时会减速
in the sense that if you look at the crests of the wave,
也就是说  这些光波的波峰
in a vacuum those crests are traveling at c, the speed of light,
在真空中会以光速 c 传播
but inside the glass those crests will be traveling a little bit slower.
而在玻璃中则会传播得稍微慢一点
And the specific ratio
而真空中的光速和介质中的光速的比值
between the speed of light in a vacuum and the speed inside a medium like this
is called the index of refraction for that medium.
就是这个介质的折射率
The reason we use the word refraction instead of the index of slowing
我们采用“折射率”而不是“减速率”这个词
is that if a beam of light enters this glass at an angle,
是因为当一束光斜着进入玻璃
then a consequence of this slowdown is that it bends a little bit,
这种减速会使这束光被略微偏折
or using the lingo, it refracts.
用专业术语说就是 它发生了折射
The way my high school physics teacher always explained this
我的高中老师通常这样解释
was to imagine a tank
想象一辆坦克
going from some region where it can travel relatively quickly, like concrete,
从一个它可以相对快速行驶的区域  比如混凝土路面
into something slower, like mud,
进到一个走起来更慢的区域  比如泥土路
where if it's coming in at an angle,
如果它斜着开进去
then as one of its treads hits the slow region first,
那么当它的一条履带先进入慢区域时
that tread will be going slower
那条履带就会变慢
while the other one is faster, causing the whole tank to steer a little bit
这样一来另一条履带就会相对较快  导致整个坦克转向
until that second tread also enters the mud, then it continues straight
直到另一边的履带进入泥地以后  坦克才会继续直行
just traveling a little slower.
只是行驶速度变慢了一点
We'll get back to the actual reason for bending in a bit,
而折射的实际原因我们稍后会说到
but at this point the high school physics students typically learn a law
在教这个的时候  高中物理学生通常会学到一个定律
known as Snell's law
叫做斯涅尔定律
which specifies exactly how much things bend.
可以准确算出光束会有多大角度偏折
If you draw a line perpendicular to the boundary between the glass and water,
如果画一条垂直于玻璃和水界面的线
and consider the angle between that perpendicular line and the beam of light,
对于光束和这条垂线的夹角大小
Snell's law tells us that
斯涅尔定律指出
the sine of this angle divided by the speed of the light is always a constant.
这个角度的正弦值除以光速始终是一个常数
So the slower the light, the lower that angle will be,
所以光速越慢  这个角度就越小
and that lets you calculate how much things refract.
也就由此可以算出光束会发生多大的折射
What's going on with a prism, then,
而棱镜的原理通常是这样解释的
is that the specific amount that light slows down depends a little bit on its frequency.
光减速的程度部分取决于它的频率
For example, blue light, which has a relatively high frequency,
例如  频率相对较高的蓝光
would get slowed down more aggressively than red light,
会比频率相对较低的红光
which has a relatively low frequency.
被更大幅地减速
Most of the light you see is not a clean pure sine wave,
你看到的大部分光不是纯净的正弦波
in particular the white light coming from the sun is not a clean sine wave,
来自太阳的白光也不是
it's something much messier,
它的波形更为复杂
but it can be expressed as a sum of a bunch of clean sine waves,
但可以表示为一系列光谱颜色
each one corresponding to a pure spectral color.
所对应的纯净正弦波的叠加
So when you shine white light into a prism like this,
当你像这样把白光照射到棱镜中时
all those different components get refracted by slightly different amounts,
它的不同光成分被折射的程度会有略微差异
causing this iconic separation of the pure rainbow colors.
从而形成彩虹色的分离
So that is the standard explanation, and it's not wrong per se,
这是常规的解释  它本身并没有错
it's just that all of the key components are handed down from on high.
只是所有的关键部分都是突然从天而降的
Why would light slow down like this?
比如 为什么光会减速呢
And what exactly do we mean by slowing down?
我们说的减速到底是什么意思呢
And even if you understand that,
即便你知道这些
why would the amount that it slows down have anything to do with the color of the light?
那么为什么光减速的程度和光的颜色有关呢？
Is that just a coincidence or is it necessary?
这是巧合还是必然呢？
If you have a sufficiently high standard for explanations,
如果你追求的是高标准的解释
you want both of these facts to feel discovered,
会想把这两个问题变得有迹可循
rather than feeling like they were handed down.
而不是像借用别人的结论
The first explanation I saw that started to give this feeling
我看到的第一个给人这种感觉的解释
came from the Feynman lectures on the matter,
来自费曼的物理学讲义
and a lot of what I'd like to do with this video is simply
而我希望在这个视频中
animate a lot of the key points that he makes there.
可以用动画的方式展示他提出的许多重点
It involves really digging in to think about each individual wiggling charge in the material
整个流程需要深入思考每一个震荡的电荷
and the propagating light waves caused by each one of those charges
以及这些电荷引起的光波传播
and how all of them superimpose on top of each other,
以及这些波全部是如何叠加的
which feels like it should be a complete mess,
乍一看理应会杂乱无章
but it actually works out to be not only understandable, but satisfyingly explanatory.
但实际这不仅可以理解  而且相当合理
For example, it explains why it has to depend on color,
比如 它可以解释为什么折射率与颜色有关
and the key intuition there really comes down to
而其中关键的直觉解释
what happens if you're bad at pushing a child on a swing.
可以类比为  用错误方式给孩子荡秋千会怎么
Bear with me, I promise that'll make sense later.
我保证稍后会讲清楚  敬请期待
Also, when I mentioned on Patreon the intention to cover this topic,
另外  当我在 Patreon 上提到打算讲这个话题时
a lot of people had a lot of questions about the index of refraction.
很多人对折射率有许多疑问
For example, numerous people asked about
例如很多人会问
how it's possible for this number to be lower than 1,
怎么可能出现折射率小于 1 的情况
which really does happen,
这确实会发生
despite that seeming to imply the impossibility of
尽管这似乎意味着事物以超光速运动
something traveling faster than the speed of light.
There was also a question about birefringence,
还有一个关于双折射的问题
which is where a material can have two different indices of refraction
即材料可以同时具有两个不同的折射率
causing you to see double when you look through it.
导致你透过材料看时会看到重影
And that actually ties in really nicely to putting in the final puzzle piece
这视频实际上恰好也是
from the last two videos about the barber pole phenomenon.
解开前两个视频里彩虹灯柱谜题的最后一环
And a couple people also asked about
还有一些人问
why light slowing down would imply a bending like this.
光减速为什么会导致光束这样弯折
And I agree, that deserves a better explanation than the tank analogy.
我也觉得这确实需要比类比坦克更好的解释
I promise we'll get to all of these questions later,
我保证以后会解答这些问题
but it makes sense to first lay down some groundwork
但是首先我们需要学习一些基础知识
by spending the bulk of our time on the key question of
为了理解为什么光波
why passing through a medium would change the speed of a light wave at all.
在通过介质时会改变速度
And for this, I want you to think of your material, like glass,
我希望你将比如玻璃的这些材料
as being broken up into a bunch of distinct layers,
想象成由许多层组成
all perpendicular to the direction the light is traveling.
每一层都垂直于光的传播方向
And we'll start by focusing our attention
我们首先把目光放在
on the effect of just one of those layers on the light wave.
其中一层材料对光波的影响
The true effect would be miniscule,
它的实际影响非常微小
but if you'll let me exaggerate it for a moment,
但是如果我稍微夸张一点
what it does is kick back the phase of the wave.
它确实使光波的相位滞后了
And maybe it's worth a brief aside
这里也许有必要插进来一些简单解释
to make sure we're all on the same page when it comes to wave terminology.
来确保我们对有关波的术语有相同的认识
If you go and graph the function sine of x,
假设有一个正弦函数 sin(x) 的图像
when you put some term in front of it,
在它前面乘一个项
affecting how high that wave oscillates up and down,
影响的是它上下波动的幅度
that's what we call the amplitude,
我们称之为振幅
when you put a term in front of x, this will affect how rapidly it oscillates.
如果在 x 前面乘以一个项 这将影响它振动的快慢
If this is meant to describe a wave over time,
如果它是用来描述随时间变化的波
that term would be called the angular frequency,
这个数称为角频率
whereas if it's meant to describe a wave over space,
如果它是用来描述随空间变化的波
that constant would be called the wave number.
这个数称为  波数
Then if you were to add some other constant inside that sine function,
如果在正弦函数里面  加上另一个常数
and notice how as you change what that constant is,
会观察到当改变这个常数时
it sort of slides the wave left and right,
波会左右平移
that term describes the phase of the wave.
这一项就代表了波的相位
So when I say that
所以我所说的
our light wave hitting a layer of glass causes its phase to get kicked back,
光波碰到一层玻璃会引起其相位的滞后
I mean if you take whatever function describes it before it hits the glass,
意思是  如果取一个函数来描述打到玻璃之前的波
then the function describing it after that looks almost the same,
那么之后的函数看起来几乎没有变化
just with a little extra something added to the input of that sine function.
只是在那个正弦函数的括号里加了一个数
Like I said, in reality that'll be a very small number,
就像刚才说的  在现实中这是一个非常小的数值
something proportional to the infinitesimal thickness of that layer,
它和那层玻璃微小的厚度成比例
but I'll keep drawing it as something exaggerated
但我会继续以夸张的程度把它画出来
and keep track of the value of that phase kick over here on the left.
并在左上角显示这个相位滞后的值
Let's say you go and add a bunch of other layers of the glass,
假设继续一层层地添加玻璃
each one also applying their own kickback to the phase of the wave.
而每一层都把波的相位滞后
The question for you is what does that new wave look like?
那么问题来了  新的波应该长什么样呢？
If the value of that phase kick applied by each layer is something really close to zero,
如果每一层产生的相位滞后都非常接近零
then the wave is hardly affected at all.
那么光波几乎不受影响
But the larger that phase kick,
但相位滞后作用越大
the more the wave kind of gets squished together among all those layers.
光波在这些层中就越像是被挤在一起
Admittedly right here it looks all kaleidoscopic and weird,
坦白说右边看起来让人眼花缭乱
but that's really just because I have a discrete set of layers,
但这实际上只是因为我用了一层层离散的玻璃
each applying an unrealistically large kick.
且每一层的滞后都离谱地大
Notice what happens if I smooth it out by doubling the density of layers,
注意当我通过翻倍层的密度而减半每层滞后来平滑它时
but having each one only apply half the phase kick.
会有怎么样的变化
And then I do that again, I double the density of the layers,
然后我再来一次  层的密度再次翻倍
but have each one only apply half the phase kick.
每一层的相位滞后再次减半
As I continue this over and over,
随着我一次次地重复这个过程
approaching a situation where you have a continuum of glass,
它逐渐接近连续玻璃的情况
each layer applying just a tiny infinitesimal phase kick,
每一层只施加一个微小的相位滞后
what you end up with is
最终得到的结果
identical to, indistinguishable from, a wave that's simply traveling slower,
完全就等价于一个跑得更慢的波
oscillating up and down with the same frequency,
它上下振荡的频率不变
but with a wavelength that's been kind of scrunched up.
但波长已经被压缩了一些
This right here is the first key idea with the index of refraction.
这就是折射率的第一个关键点
Instead of asking why does light slow down in glass,
与其问光为什么在玻璃中减速
what we really need to ask is
我们真正需要问的是
why does its interaction with a single layer of that glass
为什么它与一层玻璃的相互作用
cause a kickback to the phase of the wave.
会引起波的相位的滞后
And then when we want to get quantitative
在此之上我们想要量化
and understand exactly how much the light slows down,
弄清楚  具体减速了多少
which is critical for understanding why it depends on color,
毕竟这问题  关乎折射与色彩的关系
instead the real question is
于是  问题就变成了
how strong is that phase kick?
这个相位滞后有多大呢？
From here it's helpful to turn back to the fundamentals of what light even is.
这里回顾一下光的底层本质会很有帮助
This is something we talked a lot about in the last video,
这个内容在上期视频中说了很多
but a little review never hurts so let me go over the essentials.
但回顾一下总没坏处  所以让我简要介绍一下基本概念
As many of you know, light is a wave in the electromagnetic field,
很多观众都知道  光是电磁场中的一种波
but here we'll just be drawing the electric field.
但在这里我们只画出电场
The electric field associates each point in 3D space with a little 3-dimensional vector
电场将三维空间中每一点与一个小三维向量对应
telling you what force would be applied
这个向量告诉你
to a hypothetical unit charge sitting at that point in space.
这个点上的单位电荷会被施加什么力
The key thing going on with light is that if you have a charged particle
重点是  如果有一个带电粒子
and something causes it to wiggle up and down,
被某些原因驱使上下振动
that results in these propagating ripples in the electric field,
这会在电场中产生涟漪
away from the charge and that propagation is traveling at the speed c, the speed of light.
并沿远离电荷方向以速度 c 即光速传播
Whenever those ripples happen to reach another charged particle,
当这些涟漪遇到另一个带电粒子时
they cause it to wiggle up and down, albeit a little more weakly than the initial wiggle,
会造成那个粒子上下摆动  但程度比初始摆动稍弱
and that in turn causes its own propagations.
波传回来  又将带动自身振动
The way we described this in the last video was that
我们在上期视频中是这样描述这一点的
if at some point in time a charge is accelerating,
如果某刻一个电荷正在加速
then after a little delay, which depends on this speed c,
那么在经过一小段取决于速度 c 的延迟之后
the existence of that acceleration induces a force on another charge.
这个加速度的存在会在另一个电荷上产生力
We went over the specific force law describing this,
我们讨论过描述这一现象的具体力学定律
it's something that can be derived downstream of Maxwell's equations,
它可以用麦克斯韦方程组推导出来
but for our purposes here, the main thing to take away in your mind is that
不过对于我们现在的讨论来说  你要了解的重点是
the amount of time it takes that initial acceleration
最初的加速度  对其它位置产生的影响  传播速度恰好是 c
to cause any kind of influence elsewhere travels at exactly the speed c.
And really, you should think of c not so much as the speed of light per se,
实际上  你应该不仅仅把 c 当作是光速本身
but as the speed of causality.
它更是因果关系的速度
It determines how fast any kind of influence travels,
c 决定了任何影响所传播的速度
it's just that one of multiple consequences of that is that it's the speed of light.
而光的速度  只是其结果之一
In particular, when you get a charge oscillating up and down
特别地  当一个电荷
in a nice clean sinusoidal motion,
以纯净的正弦运动上下振荡时
you can think of these rippling effects in the electric field
你可以把它在电场中产生的涟漪
as describing the force that would be applied to another charge sitting there
看作是在描述处于其它位置的电荷
as a result of that past acceleration.
由于过去的加速度所受到的力
I will freely admit that I had a bit too much fun in that video
实话说我在上期视频里有点过于炫技
just simulating how the electric field responds to accelerating charges,
尽兴地模拟了电场如何响应加速的电荷
and that I'm kind of doing the same thing here,
而且我在这也还是在重复这个操作
but there are two important facts for our pursuit of the index of refraction.
但想弄清楚折射率  需要知道两个重要的事实
The first is that when you have multiple different charges oscillating up and down,
第一  当有多个电荷上下振荡时
the net effect on the electric field
它们对电场的净效应
is just the sum of what it would be for each individual charge,
是每一个电荷的效应之和
which is kind of what you would expect.
这大概是意料之中的
The way that it shakes out is that
但是如果考虑
if you have a row of charges oscillating in sync with each other,
有一排电荷同步振荡
or for our purposes today,
或者放到当下的讨论里
a plane of charges, all wiggling up and down in sync within that plane,
考虑一层电荷在一个平面内同步上下振荡
then the effects of each individual charge
那么每个电荷单独的效应
tend to cancel each other out in most directions,
会在大多数方向上相互抵消
except perpendicular to that plane, they actually constructively interfere.
而在垂直于平面的方向上形成相长干涉
This is how you can get a concentrated beam of light.
从而获得集中的光束
That's the important thing.
这才是重点
If you have a layer of charges wiggling up and down in sync with each other,
假设有一层电荷同步上下振荡
then even far away from that layer,
那么即使在离它很远的地方
it produces this nice sinusoidal wave in the electric field
电场中也会产生这种
that we're so fond of drawing to represent light.
我们喜欢用来表示光波形的  漂亮的正弦波
When I draw a light wave like this,
当我画这样一个光波的时候
it's really only depicting the electric field on a single one-dimensional line.
它实际上只展现了一条一维直线上的电场
A more full picture of light in three dimensions would look something more like this.
而更完整的三维空间中的图像更像是这样的
That tends to be a little bit busier, so usually we just draw the sine wave.
不过这显得太繁杂了  所以通常我们只画正弦波
So, thinking back to the question of
所以回归正题
why interactions with a layer of material would cause a kickback to the phase of the wave,
为什么与一层材料的相互作用会引起波的相位滞后
let's start thinking it through.
让我们理清一遍思路
When a light beam enters a material, like glass,
当光束进入像玻璃这样的材料时
then it causes all of the charges inside that material,
会引起材料内的各种电荷
you know, electrons, or maybe the occasional ion,
包括电子  或离子
to wiggle up and down in response to that light wave.
受到光波影响  开始上下振荡
You might think that adding together all the propagations
你可能会想  把所有电荷的传播全加在一起
from all those charges is a complete nightmare,
那将会是彻底的噩梦
but we can think about it one layer at a time.
但我们可以一层一层地考虑
As the light wave causes this layer to wiggle up and down,
当光波使这一层上下振荡时
that wiggling produces its own second-order light wave at the same frequency,
会产生一个相同频率的二阶光波
and it propagates in both directions perpendicular to that layer.
并在垂直于这层的前后两个方向上传播
The overall electric field, then,
此时整体的电场
looks like the initial incoming light wave added together with the second-order wave.
看起来就像是初始光波与二阶光波的叠加
By far the most distracting part of what's going on here is everything on the left,
目前看上去最碍眼的是  左半边的波形
and this actually corresponds to the light being reflected back.
但这实际上对应的是光被反射的部分
And from experience, you all know that when you look at water or you look at glass,
众所周知  当你看水或看玻璃时
light not only goes through it, but some of it gets reflected back.
光不只是穿过它  还会有一部分被反射回来
And we could have a whole interesting discussion on quantifying exactly how much,
单单量化反射率这个问题  已经是另一个有趣的讨论
but in the spirit of staying focused, we will completely ignore that for today,
但为了避免跑题  我们今天先完全忽略它
and only focus on what's happening to the right of that layer.
只关注光穿过那层后发生的情况
You can probably predict what I'm going to say.
你大概已经知道我要说什么了
It turns out that when you add that second-order oscillation,
事实证明  加上那个二阶振荡以后
the overall effect is almost identical to the incoming light,
它看上去和入射光的波形几乎一样
but just shifted back in phase by a little bit.
只是相位稍微往后移动了一点
And then because many successive shifts to the phase like this
而相位多次连续地像这样滞后
are the same thing as light slowing down,
也就等同于光减速了
this will ultimately explain the index of refraction.
这也就最终解释了折射率
But of course, the sufficiently curious viewers will now be raising their hands and asking,
当然了  很好奇的观众这时就会举起手问
why is that the effect when you add them together?
为什么叠加之后  效应是这样的呢？
And so here it might be worth a little sidebar
那么我们还是补充说明一下
on how to think about adding two waves together.
怎么考虑两个波的叠加
If you draw some sine wave with some particular amplitude,
要是画出一个正弦波  振幅给定
some specific frequency, and some specific phase,
频率给定  相位也给定
and then you draw another sine wave, also with its own amplitude, frequency, and phase,
然后再画另一个正弦波  另外给出振幅  频率  相位
in general, it's very hard to think about
那通常挺难回答
what the sum of those two waves should look like as you tweak those initial parameters.
要是调整以上6个参数  两波之和会变得怎样
In the specific case where the frequencies are the same,
如果对于我们的情形
which is true for our example,
假设频率是相同的
the result will also look like a sine wave with that same frequency.
那么结果也是同一频率的正弦波
But even then, it's a little tricky to think about exactly how to describe that wave.
但即便如此  想要准确描述这个波  也不太好办
It has some amplitude and some phase,
答案有一个振幅与相位
and if I ask you to concretely compute both of those numbers,
而如果我要你根据初始两波的振幅与相位
based on the amplitudes and phases of the initial waves,
具体计算叠加后的这两个参数
it's not immediately clear how you would do that
那答案与过程并不显然
without maybe throwing a bunch of trig identities at the problem.
除非你甩出一堆三角恒等式
But here's a really nice way to think about it.
不过有这样一种好思路
Imagine that first wave describes the y-component of some rotating vector.
首先想象第一个波描述的是一个旋转向量的y分量
The length of that vector corresponds with the amplitude of our wave,
向量的长度对应波的振幅
and then the initial rotation of that vector corresponds with the phase of our wave.
向量的初始角度对应波的相位
And then similarly think of that second wave
然后同样地把第二个波
as describing the y-component of another rotating vector,
当作另一个旋转向量的y分量
where again the amplitude corresponds with the length of that vector,
波的振幅还是向量的长度
and the phase of the wave tells us the initial angle of that vector.
波的相位还是向量的初始角度
Now to think about the sum of the two waves,
这时  想考虑两波之和
just think about adding those two vectors tip to tail.
只需把这两个向量首尾相连
And because they both have the same frequency as both of them rotate,
因为两者转动的频率都是相同的
their sum kind of rotates in lockstep with them.
它们的和也会跟着同步转动
So if you want to think about the amplitude of our resulting wave,
所以叠加的波的振幅
it comes down to the length of this vector sum,
就是向量之和的长度
and similarly the phase corresponds to the angle of that vector sum.
而叠加的波的相位  就对应向量值和的角度
In some cases this tells you things that you probably already knew,
对于特殊的情况  这会给出一些熟悉的结论
like if the two phases happen to be the same, then you get constructive interference
例如  如果初始相位刚好相同  就会发生相长干涉
and you have a bigger wave that results.
得到更大的波
And if the phases were 180 degrees out of sync, then you get deconstructive interference
而如果相位相差了 180 度  则会发生相消干涉
with a relatively small resulting wave.
得到更小的波
What's a little bit less obvious, but what's crucial for our discussion here,
上面的情况有点显然  但我们需要知道的关键是
is that if the phase of that second wave happens to be
如果第二个波的相位
exactly 90 degrees behind the phase of the first,
刚好比第一个波滞后了90度
so kind of a quarter cycle out of sync,
也就是1/4周期的不同步
and if that second wave is also very small compared to the first,
而且第二个波远小于第一个波
then if you look at the little vector sum on the lower left,
那么注意看左下角的向量和
you'll notice how this means that the resulting wave is almost identical to the initial wave,
就会发现  所得的波形  跟第一个波几乎相同
but just shifted back in its phase by a tiny bit.
只是相位后移了一丁点
Moreover, the size of that phase shift
而且  这个相位滞后的值
depends on the specific amplitude of that second wave.
正比于第二个波的振幅
So looking back at our previous animation,
于是  回去看前面的动画
where we have some wiggling charges in a layer of glass
一层玻璃中有一些振动的电子
causing these second order propagations
导致二阶震荡传播
that need to be added together with the incoming light,
需要与入射光线相叠加
the way it works out is that the phase of that second wave
这时发生的是  第二个波的相位
is exactly a quarter of a cycle behind the phase of the first.
恰好比第一个波滞后了1/4个周期
So when you add them together, you get this little phase shift.
因此叠加以后  就会出现相位的后移
And then, critically,
而且  关键是
the size of that phase shift is bigger when that second order wave is larger,
二阶的波越大  相位滞后也越大
and then smaller when that second order wave is smaller.
二阶的波越小  相位滞后也越小
Again, the very curious viewers will be raising their hands and saying,
当然了  很好奇的观众又会举起手来说
why does it work out to be exactly a quarter of a cycle behind?
为什么刚好滞后了1/4个周期啊
There is a very nice reason, but it's just a little too much detail for us today.
这背后有个道理  但细节太多  不适合今天讲
If you're curious,
感兴趣的话
I highly encourage you to take a look at the Feynman lectures on the matter.
我强烈推荐你去看费曼讲义的解释
For our purposes, step back for a second
我们还是退一步  回到正题
and think about what you need to explain the key question of prisms,
想想需要用什么来解释棱镜的关键问题：
which is why the index of refraction would depend on color at all.
究竟为什么折射率会跟色彩有关呢
As you now know, that index depends on how much each layer of glass
我们现在知道  折射率取决于每一层玻璃
kicks back the phase of the wave,
把波的相位滞后了多少
and that phase kick depends on the strength of the second order wave
而相位的滞后  取决于二阶波的强度
resulting from charge oscillations in a layer of that glass.
而二阶波来源于每层玻璃中的电荷振荡
So you need to drill in and understand
所以我们要刨根问底  去搞懂
exactly how much those charges wiggle in response to an incoming light wave.
入射光波激起的电荷振荡  准确值是多大
So let's zoom in on that layer and think of each one of those charged particles,
我们放大到那一层  考虑每一个带电粒子
and even though the specific molecular structure is going to be something very complicated
虽然具体的分子结构将会十分复杂
we're going to model each one of those charges
但我们用简单的模型来表示电荷
as if it was bound to some equilibrium position by a spring,
把它们看作由一个或一组弹簧
or maybe a set of springs.
限制到平衡位置
I don't mean this literally, of course,
当然我不是说真有弹簧
I just mean if we describe the displacement of this charge from its equilibrium
而是说  如果我们把电荷离平衡点的位移
with a little vector x that's going to depend on time,
记作向量 x  会随时间变化
then in our model, the force applied to the charge,
那么在模型中  电荷所受的
pulling it back to that equilibrium,
指向平衡点的力
is going to be something proportional to the size of that displacement,
将跟位移向量的大小成正比
with a little proportionality constant k.
比例系数记作k
This is the same law that governs how springs work.
这跟弹簧所满足的胡克定律是一样的
You might ask if that's accurate,
你也许会问  这准确吗
and the idea is that for very small displacements,
道理是  对于很小的位移
it's actually a really good approximation.
这是非常好的近似
This is a very common thing to do throughout physics,
这在物理中很常用
we would call it a linear restoring force.
叫做  线性回复力
The idea is that maybe the actual force law depends on the position
想法是  虽然实际的力随位置的变化
in a much more complicated way,
可能会复杂得多
but we're basically taking a low order approximation near the equilibrium.
但是我们这里只是在取平衡附近的低阶近似
If I just run this as a simulation, plugging in this force law,
我来跑一个仿真程序  代入这个力的表达式
here's what that displacement looks like as a function of time.
这就是位移对时间的函数
What you get looks like a sine wave, this is called simple harmonic motion,
得到的这种正弦波  叫做简谐运动
and the frequency of this wave is going to matter a lot for you and me,
这个波的频率  是我们最为关心的
and finding that comes down to solving a certain differential equation,
而想要求这个频率  就要解某个微分方程
because the force is really the same thing as mass times acceleration,
因为力  等于质量乘以加速度
and the acceleration is the same thing as the second derivative of that displacement.
而加速度  就是位移的二阶导数
So what we're saying is we want some function
所以我们想要找的函数满足
whose second derivative looks like a certain constant times that function itself.
二阶导等于自身的某个负的常数倍
Many differential equations students among you
在学习微分方程的同学们
might enjoy thinking about how you solve this.
也许要想想这得怎么解
I won't go over the full details, but the answer is reasonably intuitive,
我就不展开讲细节了  不过答案挺直观
and anyone who knows a little calculus can just check it for themselves.
懂一点微积分就可以自己检查一下
The way it shakes out is that
这个方程的结果是
if the initial condition is that our little charge has a velocity of zero,
如果初始条件是  小电荷初始速度为0
but it's offset from the equilibrium by a little vector x₀,
而离平衡点的位移是小向量x₀
then the way it evolves over time looks like x₀ multiplied by a cosine expression.
那么其位移随时间的函数是  x₀乘以一个余弦
So the amplitude of this wave is kind of uninteresting,
这个波的振幅不大有趣
it just depends on how far we pull things back originally,
只是取决于一开始电荷移了多远
but the meat is this frequency term, square root of k divided by m.
但精华所在是这个频率  根号下 k/m
And if you think about it, this should hopefully be at least a little intuitive.
你想一想  这其实还挺符合直觉的
For example, if you increase k, which is kind of like increasing the strength of that spring,
例如  增加 k  就好比把弹簧变硬
then it results in a faster oscillation.
那么振荡会变快
Whereas if you increase m, the mass of the particle,
而增加 m  粒子的质量
there's a lot more inertia, and it results in a slower oscillation.
那惯性会更大  振荡会变慢
This term, square root of k divided by m, has a special name,
这一项  根号下 k/m  有一个术语
it's called the resonant frequency for our simple harmonic oscillator.
叫做简谐振子的共振频率
And being a little more precise, I should call this the resonant angular frequency.
更准确一点  应该叫共振角频率
This is always a little bit of an awkwardness with physics,
物理中总是有这种小麻烦
where whenever you have some kind of cyclic process,
每当你碰到周期性的过程
when you give an intuitive description,
想要直观地描述时
it's natural to phrase things in terms of the frequency,
自然会提到频率
the number of cycles that this process makes per unit time.
也就是单位时间中  这个过程所经历的周期数
But when doing math, it's often more natural to talk about the angular frequency,
但做数学推导时  往往更为自然的是角频率
which you could think of as describing how much angle this process covers in radians per unit time.
那就是单位时间中  这个过程所扫过的弧度
So the term is the same as the frequency but multiplied by 2π.
所以角频率  等于频率再乘以 2π 倍
So for example, if you have something like a cosine expression,
例如  对于这样一个余弦表达式
which you might think of as describing the x-component of a cycling vector like this,
可以看作描述的是  旋转向量的x分量
then the term sitting right in front of the t in that cosine is the angular frequency.
那么在余弦中  t 前面的系数  就是角频率
This is why angular frequency makes the math a little cleaner.
因此用角频率  数学式子看着更简洁
For example, in our simple harmonic motion,
例如  回到我们的简谐运动
the term sitting in front of t looks like the square root of k divided by m,
t 前面的项  是根号下 k/m
which I'm writing as ωᵣ.
我记作 ωᵣ
Let's package all of that up and call that our solution in the simple case,
总结起来  这就是简单情形的方程的解
where there's no external force acting on our charged particle.
这里假设带电粒子没有受到外力
But of course, what we're interested in
但当然了  我们关心的是
is what happens when you shine a beam of light on this material,
当光束入射到材料时的情形
which intuitively causes this charge to jiggle,
直觉上  电荷会因此振动
but the question is how much.
但问题是振幅的大小
In our equation, this looks like adding a new force term corresponding to the light wave.
这就像在方程右侧  加一项新的力  代表入射光
That force oscillates up and down also according to some kind of cosine function,
这个力的上下振荡  也遵循余弦函数
but this time with a distinct angular frequency that I'm going to call ωₗ.
但它另外有一个角频率  就叫 ωₗ 吧
E₀ here describes the strength of the wave,
这里的 E₀ 代表光波的强度
and then q describes the charge of whatever particle we're modeling.
q 代表我们关心的粒子的电荷
As usual, it's a lot easier to think about when we only draw a subset of that light wave,
我们依旧只画出一部分光波  这样会比较清晰
and in this case we're going to draw it on the plane of the layer of material we care about.
这里显示的平面  是我们所关注的一层材料
You might think of gusts of wind blowing our little ball on the spring
可以想象成  对弹簧上的小球  吹一股风
up and down in a clean sinusoidal pattern.
风力一上一下  是正弦的样子
Or as another analogy, it's similar to pushing a child on a swing.
或者换一个比喻  像是推秋千上的孩子
The swing would oscillate on its own due to the force of gravity,
秋千本身也会因为重力  自己摇动
but you as the pusher are applying an external force which itself is oscillating over time.
但你对它施加的外力  也是周期振荡的
Although a key difference here is that the frequency of that external force
关键的区别是  外力的频率
in general has nothing to do with the resonant frequency of that little oscillator.
通常跟振子固有的共振频率  没有什么关系
The better analogy would be if you're pushing the child on the swing with a cyclic force
更好的比喻是  你推的秋千  外力的周期
that has nothing to do with what the swing naturally wants to do.
跟秋千本身想要的振荡  毫无关系
And my favorite part in literally trying to do this with my niece
说件趣事  我真的这样跟小侄女玩的时候
is that at some point she gently murmurs to herself,
她暗暗说了一句
this isn't how mom does it.
妈妈不是这样推的
Now, in trying to understand how much our charge is oscillating
那么  想要理解这里的电荷  由于入射光
in response to the incoming light,
而造成的振幅
let me start by just simulating it and plotting the result.
让我先仿真一下  画出结论
You'll notice that there's a little start-up period
注意到开始有一段启动期
where it kind of has to get going,
从零开始被带动起来
but then after that, mercifully,
但还好  在此之后
it looks nice and clean, just like another sine wave.
结果干净又漂亮  就像一个正弦波
Now you might be thinking, yeah yeah, everything is sine waves,
这时你也许想  对对  一切都是正弦波
but it's important to understand that
不过重要的是
this one has a very different character from the sine wave we saw earlier.
这跟我们之前看到的正弦波还是很不一样的
Earlier, without any external forces,
之前  没有外力时
the frequency of that wave came down to the spring constant and the mass,
波的频率取决于弹簧常数与振子质量
which is to say, it depends exclusively on material properties of the glass.
或者说  只跟玻璃的材料性质有关
By contrast, with this external cycling driving force,
而这里  有周期性外力时
the frequency in that steady state is the same as the frequency of the light.
稳态波的频率  等于入射光的频率
And then in our first case, the amplitude of the wave was kind of uninteresting,
在简单的情形  波的振幅无关紧要
it just depends on how far you pulled the spring out to begin with.
只取决于弹簧被拉了多远
But in the second case,
但有外力时
the amplitude of this wave is actually where all the interesting stuff happens.
稳态波的振幅  才是最值得关注的信息
Exactly how much will this charge be oscillating in response to the light wave?
由于入射光  电荷的振荡有多大呢？
Again, I won't go over the full details of solving this,
我依旧跳过解方程的过程
but any eager calculus students among you might enjoy going through the exercise
喜欢微积分的同学们欢迎做做这个习题
where if you just guess that a solution looks like a cosine wave
先猜解的形式是余弦波
with the same frequency as the light,
频率跟入射光相同
and you solve for the amplitude,
然后去求解振幅
you can get a concrete solution to this equation that looks like this.
方程具体的解  长这个样子
This is worth unpacking for a bit, and just to be clear,
我们来慢慢消化一下  不过首先强调一下
this is only describing things in the steady state,
这只是在描述稳态的解
after things have gotten up and going.
而不包括前期的部分
A fully descriptive solution would be notably more complicated.
完整的解看着会复杂得多
As I said, everything interesting here comes down to the amplitude,
我也说过  最重要的信息是这个振幅
which here looks like a large collection of constants,
它看着包含了许多的参数
most of which should be pretty intuitive if you take a moment to think about it.
想一想的话  基本还是挺直观的
For example, it is proportional to the strength of that incoming light wave,
例如  振幅正比于入射的光强
so the stronger the light the more the oscillations.
入射光越强  振荡也越大
It's also proportional to the charge, which again makes sense.
振幅也正比于电荷  很合理
And the real heart of the matter comes down to what's sitting in the denominator here,
而真正的核心在于分母的这部分：
the difference between the square of the resonant frequency
共振频率的平方  减去
and the square of the light frequency.
光波频率的平方
And to build a little intuition,
为了培养一下直觉
take a moment to think about what would happen if the frequency of the incoming light
我们稍微想一想  如果入射光的频率
was something very close to the resonant frequency of this oscillator.
跟振子的共振频率很接近时  会怎样
This is analogous to the normal situation pushing a child on a swing,
这就像秋千上推小孩时
where the frequency of your force lines up quite closely with what the swing wants to do.
你推动的频率  跟秋千本身的节奏  相一致
In this case, running the simulation,
这时  跑一跑程序
notice how the oscillations of that particle will grow and grow and grow,
注意到粒子的振动会不断不断增大
becoming quite large over time.
长时间后会变得很大
Some of you may know the famous example of the Millennium Bridge in London,
你们也许知道  伦敦千禧桥这个有名的例子
where on its opening day it started oscillating way more than the engineers expected it to.
在正式开放时  桥的振动远超出工程师的预期
And what was going on is that
原因是这样的
the frequency of the steps of the crowd lined up very closely with a resonant frequency,
人群的步频  非常接近桥的共振频率
causing this worryingly high amplitude.
因此振幅变得太大
By contrast, notice what happens in the simulation
作为对比  我们看看另一个演示
if the frequency of the light, ωₗ,
这时光的频率 ωₗ
is something much smaller than the resonant frequency.
比材料的共振频率要小得多
For this particular simulation it takes a little bit of a moment
对这个例子  要过好一阵子
before things get into their full swing.
振动才慢慢稳定下来
Eventually it finds a nice sinusoidal motion,
还是能接近正弦的波形
but the amplitude of that motion is much more modest in comparison.
只是这个振幅  相对就小得多
So what our equation is telling us
因此  方程告诉我们的是
is that the larger the difference between those frequencies,
这两个频率之间的差别越大
then the bigger the denominator,
分母也越大
so the smaller the overall wiggle to that charge.
最后电荷的振幅也就越小
And again, this is something you can see in the footage with my niece.
在小侄女的录像中你也能看到这个现象
As I'm applying a force with a frequency
当我施加的外力频率
that's very different from what the swing wants to do,
跟秋千的固有频率相差甚大的时候
she ends up oscillating at the same frequency as my force,
侄女的摇动频率跟外力一样
but she's going at a relatively low amplitude.
但振幅就比较小了
Stepping back, what this means is that as you shine light into a material, like glass,
回过头来  这说明  当你对着玻璃照进一束光
it's not just that it induces wiggles in the charges of that material,
不仅会激起材料中电荷的振荡
but the specific size of those wiggles depends on the frequency of the light,
而且这个具体的振幅  也取决于入射光的频率
as a consequence of this denominator term.
因为有分母这一项
And the more those wiggle,
而这个振荡越大
the bigger the size of this second order wave caused by that layer,
那层材料带来的二阶波动也越大
which in turn causes a bigger shift to the phase of the overall wave.
于是叠加后的波  相位的滞后也越大
Because a lot of different shifts to the phase
而因为相位的许多小滞后
are what causes this apparent slowdown to the light,
会使得光速看上去变慢
it means that the amount that it will slow down
这意味着  折射率  即光速的减慢
ultimately depends on the frequency of the light.
最后归结于入射光的频率
So that is the real reason why prisms work.
这也就是棱镜的真正原理
You cannot truly explain the light separation
想要真正解释白光的色散
until you get down to the driven harmonic oscillator.
必须要深入到  谐振子的受迫振动
Now, I have left out a number of details,
这里我跳过了几个细节
and again, I encourage the curious viewers to take a look at the Feynman lectures
我再次鼓励好奇的观众去看一看费曼讲义
that a lot of this is based on.
那是本期视频的主要参考
One quite important detail that would be a little criminal not to mention
有一个不得不提的重要细节
is that when we're modeling our charge
就是当我们把电荷建模为
as a little harmonic oscillator with this linear restoring force,
带线性回复力的简谐振子时
there should really also be a term that depends on the velocity of that charge.
其实应该有关于电荷速度的一项
You might think of this as a kind of drag force.
可以看作是一种阻力
This term accounts for the fact that energy from the incoming light wave
它考虑到的是  入射光波的能量
is absorbed by the material.
会被材料所吸收
Without it, this whole explanation would seem to imply that
少了这一项  我们的解释似乎会说
light always passes through every material, not just glass and water,
光总会透过所有材料  而不只是玻璃和水
when as you can tell just by looking around,
但你到处看看就知道
there's all sorts of materials for which light is mostly reflected and absorbed.
有许多材料  主要会反射和吸收光
As I mentioned at the start,
我最开始就提到
folks on Patreon had numerous questions about the index of refraction,
Patreon 资助者们对折射率提出了许多问题
like how it can be less than one, and why slowing implies bending,
例如  为什么可以小于一  为什么变慢会导致偏折
so I made a supplemental video answering a handful of those questions,
所以我做了一期补充视频  来解答其中一些疑问
which should be published in just a few days.
会晚一点再发
In the meantime, my friend Mythina from the channel Looking Glass Universe
在此之前  我的朋友 Mythina 在另一个频道
just put out a pair of videos on the related but definitely distinct question
发了两期视频  讲的是另一个很相关的问题
of whether light slows down in a medium,
就是  介质中  光所谓的减速
not in the sense of following the crests of a clean pure sine wave in a steady state,
除了表示  稳态正弦波峰之间距离的变小
but in the sense of trying to send information through that medium,
是否也表示  在介质中信息传播的速度变慢了呢？
like with a little wave packet.
例如小波包会怎样传播？
I definitely owe the existence of this video
我可以说  没有跟 Mythina 的讨论
to many conversations with her about this topic,
就没有这一期视频
and viewers here will definitely enjoy taking a look, especially at the second one.
我相信观众们会喜欢她的视频  尤其第二个
By the way, some collaborators and I made this notebook
最后一提  我跟合作者设计了这个笔记本
that I think a lot of viewers might enjoy,
我想你们会喜欢的
and given that it's the holiday season it seems worth a quick mention.
所以我在年底节假日打个广告
The premise is that every one of the pages has a quote that's related to math,
卖点是  每一页都有数学相关的名人名言
and I had a lot of fun curating them all,
这些都是我精心挑选的
trying to constrain myself to quotes conveying some genuinely thought-provoking idea.
我的标准是  要表达真正引人深思的想法
And then aside from the content,
除了内容本身
I basically made the kind of notebook that I most enjoy taking notes in,
我是按照自己喜欢写笔记的样子  来设计的
something that's readily portable with very faint gridlines helpful for diagrams,
要小巧好带  要有浅色的网格方便画图
but otherwise unobtrusive,
但不影响写字和阅读
all bound in this nice soft faux leather.
封皮是柔软的人造皮
If that seems up your alley,
喜欢的话
you can find them in the 3blue1brown store
可以去 3blue1brown 网店选购
next to a lot of other mathematical merchandise.
还有很多其他数学周边商品